<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
   
   	<title>blm.io - Tag: webdev</title>
   
   <link>https://blm.io</link>
   <description>Data blog from benjaminlmoore.</description>
   <language>en-us</language>
   <managingEditor>B.L. Moore</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

    
	  <item>
        <title>UK general election polls in rCharts and shiny</title>
        <link>https://blm.io/blog/uk-general-election-rcharts-shiny</link>
		<author>benjaminlmoore</author>
		<pubDate>2015-04-28T00:00:00+01:00</pubDate>
		<guid>https://blm.io/blog/uk-general-election-rcharts-shiny</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[
		   <p>With under two weeks to go to the 2015 UK general election, there&#39;s no better time to take stock of all the voter intention polls being published by the British media. The data has already been aggregated by <a href="http://ukpollingreport.co.uk/voting-intention-2">UKpollingreport</a>—a site I&#39;ve used before for <a href="https://blm.io/blog/scottish-independence-polls/">analysis of the Scottish independence referendum</a>—and there&#39;s not much more to be said then is already widely known: it&#39;s likely no single party will win an outright majority and we&#39;ll be left with a coalition or minority government.</p>

<p>Interactive visualisations, statistical projections and swingometers have already been expertly put together all over the place (among the best I&#39;ve seen are from <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/ng-interactive/2015/feb/27/guardian-poll-projection">The Guardian</a> and <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/interactives/uk-general-election-predictions/">FiveThirtyEight</a>)—I can&#39;t really begin to compete here, but given the data is readily available, I&#39;ve taken this as a good chance to finally learn shiny and build a simple web application.</p>

<h2>Interactive javascript plot</h2>

<style>
div.highcharts-container{
    margin: 0 auto !important;
};
</style>

<p>Before getting to shiny, I started off I started by putting together an interactive (client-side) javascript plot using the <a href="http://rcharts.io/">rCharts</a> package (specifically the <a href="http://www.highcharts.com/">Highcharts library</a>).</p>

<div id='ge2015' class="rChart"></div>

<script src="/blog/js/ge2015.js"></script>

<p><br />
This already comes with some neat functionality: as well as tooltips you can drag over an area to zoom in, and you can add or remove series by (de)selecting them from the legend. However any more complicated processing, especially on the raw data, would be better run server-side.</p>

<h2> Shiny</h2>

<p>Enter RStudio&#39;s <a href="http://shiny.rstudio.com/">shiny</a>, the much-lauded web application framework for R which I&#39;m well-overdue in trying out. Better still, RStudio&#39;s <a href="http://www.shinyapps.io/">shinyapps</a> hosting service is now out of beta and offers a limited free plan for anyone to play about with!</p>

<p>To start out with I redesigned the above plot in <code>ggplot2</code> (you can see the code <a href="https://github.com/blmoore/blogR/blob/master/R/ge2015_polls.R">on github</a>):</p>

<p><a href="/blog/img/ge2015_ggplot_full.png" target="_blank">
<img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/ge2015_ggplot_thumb.png" />
</a></p>

<p>Of course, it&#39;s possible to use shiny to draw javascript plots but for this example I just wanted to replicate the same kind of functionality—while also extending the shiny version with features that would probably need to be pre-computed in a client-side plot (such as aggregating counts by week and refitting loess models per group).</p>

<p>Next with the help of Rstudio&#39;s <a href="http://shiny.rstudio.com/tutorial/">shiny tutorials</a>, it was surprisingly straightforward to add a couple of control widgets and pass their values over to the server-side script which does the heavy lifting (code is again <a href="https://github.com/blmoore/blogR/tree/master/shiny/ge2015">on github</a>).</p>

<p><a href="http://blmr.shinyapps.io/ge2015/" target="_blank">
<img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/ge2015_shiny.png" />
</a></p>

<p>The <a href="https://blmr.shinyapps.io/ge2015/">end-result</a> is still rudimentary, but has shown me how simple shiny is to get started with—I&#39;m certain I&#39;ll be building something more impressive with it in future!</p>

<p><hr /></p>

<p style="text-align:right; font-size: .85rem;">R code to reproduce these
plots is available on
<a href="https://github.com/blmoore/blogR" target="_blank">Github</a>.</p>

		]]></description>
	  </item>
    
	  <item>
        <title>Building an academic CV in markdown</title>
        <link>https://blm.io/blog/markdown-academic-cv</link>
		<author>benjaminlmoore</author>
		<pubDate>2015-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</pubDate>
		<guid>https://blm.io/blog/markdown-academic-cv</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[
		   <p>I&#39;m creeping towards the tail-end of my PhD so it&#39;s probably time to dust off my CV and tidy it up. In the past I&#39;ve written this document a few different ways, from LaTeX to a custom <a href="https://inkscape.org/en/">Inkscape</a> document, but I&#39;ve decided to move with the times and try something new: a markdown CV that compiles to both an HTML web version and well-formatted PDF.</p>

<h2>markdown-cv</h2>

<p>Googling &quot;markdown CV&quot; gave a few different options: one using <a href="http://mszep.github.io/pandoc_resume/">pandoc</a> with slightly dated-looking themes; another <a href="http://there4development.com/blog/2012/12/31/markdown-resume-builder/">command-line PHP script</a>, whose results are a bit prettier, but after trying these I came across <code>markdown-cv</code> from github user <a href="https://github.com/elipapa/markdown-cv">elipapa</a> which seemed to be simple to use and came with a nice design &mdash; also it&#39;s built with <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">jekyll</a>, which I already <a href="https://blm.io/blog/wordpress-to-jekyll/">use to power blm.io</a>.</p>

<p>Eliseo Papa wrote up a <a href="http://www.eliseopapa.org/workflow/2012/09/20/why-i-switched-to-markdown-for-my-cv/">blog post</a> on how and why he put <code>markdown-cv</code> together, and their CV <a href="https://github.com/elipapa/elipapa.github.io/blob/master/downloads/cv.pdf">looks great</a> so that was enough to convince me to give it a shot.</p>

<h3>HTML version</h3>

<p><code>markdown-cv</code> uses CSS media queries to select different stylesheets for screen and print. This means in practice you can optimise your CV design for each medium pretty easily &mdash; I went with a kind of colourful web version and more toned-down print version.</p>

<p>I didn&#39;t make any big changes to <a href="https://github.com/elipapa/markdown-cv">elipapa&#39;s markdown-cv</a>, just played with the colours, fonts, and tweaked the layout and added <a href="http://fortawesome.github.io/Font-Awesome/">font-awesome icons</a>.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s a screenshot of the current HTML version of my CV:</p>

<p><a href="/blog/img/html-mdcv.png" target="_blank">
<img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/html-mdcv.png" />
</a></p>

<p>I like the whitespace and clear separation of headings, dates and details. The underlying CSS layout has some technical issues &mdash; the relative positions can get messed up on resize &mdash; but it still looks good on mobile devices and at a range of display resolutions.</p>

<h3>PDF version</h3>

<p><img class="imgright" src="/blog/img/printcv-ul.png" width="40%" /></p>

<p>There were a few difficulties converting the web version to print. The general approach for CVs in markdown seems to be to run <a href="http://wkhtmltopdf.org/">wkhtmltopdf</a>, however this uses WebKit for rendering (as the name suggests) which it turns out has issues with some modern CSS features when printing.</p>

<p>One issue was with CSS3 multiple <code>columns</code> layout, with <code>wkhtmltopdf</code> these were rendered in a single column while the web version renders correctly in 3-columns, across modern browsers.</p>

<p><img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/webcv-ul.png" /></p>

<p>It turns out support was <a href="https://www.webkit.org/blog/88/css3-multi-column-support/#comment-16854">dropped</a> for printing columns specified in this way due to issues with page breaks, and apparently this still hasn&#39;t been resolved. To get around this, I convert to PDF through Firefox with its <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/Gecko">Gecko engine</a> and all is well.</p>

<p><img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/printcv-ulfixed.png" /></p>

<p>Page breaks can still be iffy though, web renderers are no LaTeX, so if it doesn&#39;t break cleanly over pages you can add these in manually using CSS. For example, say you want to add a page break before your publications section:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><code>cv.md</code></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">## Publications

You _et al._ (2014) Some great paper...
</code></pre></div>
<blockquote>
<p><code>cv-print.css</code></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-css" data-lang="css"><span class="nf">#publications</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">page</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">break</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">before</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">always</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div>
<p>There&#39;s another issue I can&#39;t debug relating to web links in the PDF version (currently some work, some don&#39;t), but in theory the PDF is for print so maybe it doesn&#39;t matter.</p>

<h3>Result</h3>

<p>Here&#39;s what I have so far (click through to see the full versions) &mdash; the code is <a href="https://github.com/blmoore/md-cv">on github</a> if you want to adapt it for your own use! All credit goes to the <a href="https://github.com/elipapa/markdown-cv">original author</a> of markdown-cv.</p>

<div style="float:right; width:49%;">
  <p style="text-align:center; color:#888; font-weight: bold;">PDF</p>
  <a href="https://github.com/blmoore/md-cv/blob/master/blm_cv.pdf" target="_blank">
    <img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/printcv.png" />
  </a>
</div>

<div style="float:right; width:49%;">
  <p style="text-align:center; color:#888; font-weight: bold;">HTML</p>
  <a href="https://blm.io/cv/" target="_blank">
    <img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/webcv.png" />
    </a>
</div>

<p><br clear="all" /></p>

		]]></description>
	  </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
