<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
   
   	<title>blm.io - Tag: jekyll</title>
   
   <link>https://blm.io</link>
   <description>Data blog from benjaminlmoore.</description>
   <language>en-us</language>
   <managingEditor>B.L. Moore</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

    
	  <item>
        <title>Building an academic CV in markdown</title>
        <link>https://blm.io/blog/markdown-academic-cv</link>
		<author>benjaminlmoore</author>
		<pubDate>2015-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</pubDate>
		<guid>https://blm.io/blog/markdown-academic-cv</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[
		   <p>I&#39;m creeping towards the tail-end of my PhD so it&#39;s probably time to dust off my CV and tidy it up. In the past I&#39;ve written this document a few different ways, from LaTeX to a custom <a href="https://inkscape.org/en/">Inkscape</a> document, but I&#39;ve decided to move with the times and try something new: a markdown CV that compiles to both an HTML web version and well-formatted PDF.</p>

<h2>markdown-cv</h2>

<p>Googling &quot;markdown CV&quot; gave a few different options: one using <a href="http://mszep.github.io/pandoc_resume/">pandoc</a> with slightly dated-looking themes; another <a href="http://there4development.com/blog/2012/12/31/markdown-resume-builder/">command-line PHP script</a>, whose results are a bit prettier, but after trying these I came across <code>markdown-cv</code> from github user <a href="https://github.com/elipapa/markdown-cv">elipapa</a> which seemed to be simple to use and came with a nice design &mdash; also it&#39;s built with <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">jekyll</a>, which I already <a href="https://blm.io/blog/wordpress-to-jekyll/">use to power blm.io</a>.</p>

<p>Eliseo Papa wrote up a <a href="http://www.eliseopapa.org/workflow/2012/09/20/why-i-switched-to-markdown-for-my-cv/">blog post</a> on how and why he put <code>markdown-cv</code> together, and their CV <a href="https://github.com/elipapa/elipapa.github.io/blob/master/downloads/cv.pdf">looks great</a> so that was enough to convince me to give it a shot.</p>

<h3>HTML version</h3>

<p><code>markdown-cv</code> uses CSS media queries to select different stylesheets for screen and print. This means in practice you can optimise your CV design for each medium pretty easily &mdash; I went with a kind of colourful web version and more toned-down print version.</p>

<p>I didn&#39;t make any big changes to <a href="https://github.com/elipapa/markdown-cv">elipapa&#39;s markdown-cv</a>, just played with the colours, fonts, and tweaked the layout and added <a href="http://fortawesome.github.io/Font-Awesome/">font-awesome icons</a>.</p>

<p>Here&#39;s a screenshot of the current HTML version of my CV:</p>

<p><a href="/blog/img/html-mdcv.png" target="_blank">
<img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/html-mdcv.png" />
</a></p>

<p>I like the whitespace and clear separation of headings, dates and details. The underlying CSS layout has some technical issues &mdash; the relative positions can get messed up on resize &mdash; but it still looks good on mobile devices and at a range of display resolutions.</p>

<h3>PDF version</h3>

<p><img class="imgright" src="/blog/img/printcv-ul.png" width="40%" /></p>

<p>There were a few difficulties converting the web version to print. The general approach for CVs in markdown seems to be to run <a href="http://wkhtmltopdf.org/">wkhtmltopdf</a>, however this uses WebKit for rendering (as the name suggests) which it turns out has issues with some modern CSS features when printing.</p>

<p>One issue was with CSS3 multiple <code>columns</code> layout, with <code>wkhtmltopdf</code> these were rendered in a single column while the web version renders correctly in 3-columns, across modern browsers.</p>

<p><img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/webcv-ul.png" /></p>

<p>It turns out support was <a href="https://www.webkit.org/blog/88/css3-multi-column-support/#comment-16854">dropped</a> for printing columns specified in this way due to issues with page breaks, and apparently this still hasn&#39;t been resolved. To get around this, I convert to PDF through Firefox with its <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/Gecko">Gecko engine</a> and all is well.</p>

<p><img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/printcv-ulfixed.png" /></p>

<p>Page breaks can still be iffy though, web renderers are no LaTeX, so if it doesn&#39;t break cleanly over pages you can add these in manually using CSS. For example, say you want to add a page break before your publications section:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><code>cv.md</code></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">## Publications

You _et al._ (2014) Some great paper...
</code></pre></div>
<blockquote>
<p><code>cv-print.css</code></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-css" data-lang="css"><span class="nf">#publications</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">page</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">break</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">before</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="k">always</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div>
<p>There&#39;s another issue I can&#39;t debug relating to web links in the PDF version (currently some work, some don&#39;t), but in theory the PDF is for print so maybe it doesn&#39;t matter.</p>

<h3>Result</h3>

<p>Here&#39;s what I have so far (click through to see the full versions) &mdash; the code is <a href="https://github.com/blmoore/md-cv">on github</a> if you want to adapt it for your own use! All credit goes to the <a href="https://github.com/elipapa/markdown-cv">original author</a> of markdown-cv.</p>

<div style="float:right; width:49%;">
  <p style="text-align:center; color:#888; font-weight: bold;">PDF</p>
  <a href="https://github.com/blmoore/md-cv/blob/master/blm_cv.pdf" target="_blank">
    <img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/printcv.png" />
  </a>
</div>

<div style="float:right; width:49%;">
  <p style="text-align:center; color:#888; font-weight: bold;">HTML</p>
  <a href="https://blm.io/cv/" target="_blank">
    <img class="imgfull" src="/blog/img/webcv.png" />
    </a>
</div>

<p><br clear="all" /></p>

		]]></description>
	  </item>
    
	  <item>
        <title>Transformation of wordpress into jekyll</title>
        <link>https://blm.io/blog/wordpress-to-jekyll</link>
		<author>benjaminlmoore</author>
		<pubDate>2014-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</pubDate>
		<guid>https://blm.io/blog/wordpress-to-jekyll</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[
		   <p>I think <a href="http://wordpress.org/">Wordpress</a> is a great <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_management_system">CMS</a> and I&#39;m reluctant to leave it behind. While
it doesn&#39;t have much hacker kudos, in my opinion (and undoubtedly many others)
Wordpress is a very usable and near-complete blogging
platform which doesn&#39;t leave much justification for reinventing the wheel. It also seems to have reached
a kind of critical mass where it&#39;s own &quot;like&quot; and &quot;follow&quot; features are
useful tools, with the latter a decent way of building an audience that
don&#39;t use RSS readers and aren&#39;t interested in the extra cruft that comes with twitter. In fact, my Wordpress blog currently has
more followers than my twitter account, and I suspect a higher <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Click-through_rate">CTR</a> per
post. So with that in mind, why am I making the switch?</p>

<p>In short, it&#39;s due to two factors:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>The <a href="https://pages.github.com/">Github pages</a> system offering free hosting
with custom domains, all built on top of a normal git repo.</p></li>
<li><p>The <a href="http://rcharts.io">rCharts</a> R package which, to me as a non-web guy,
has acted as a great intro to various <a href="https://d3js.org/">D3.js</a>-based plotting
libraries, and piqued my interest in building custom interactive graphics.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>My blog setup was getting increasingly messy, usually with a full write-up
on <a href="https://wordpress.com/">hosted wordpress</a> &mdash; to take advantage of the existing audience there &mdash; with accompanying interactive plots hosted here. The problem with this is that the javascript plots were usually the most interesting part of the post, but were buried in external links due to wordpress limitations. Plus this split would divide social shares and search traffic (not that I&#39;m attempting any SEO or real monetisation but it&#39;s nice if people occasionally read my stuff).</p>

<p><img src="/blog/img/jekyll.png" class="imgright" width="200px" height="110px" />
After researching my options, I&#39;m now using <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> (aided by <a href="https://github.com/poole/poole">poole</a> during setup). With Github pages hosting, Github will run Jekyll on their servers, building your site when you push commits, but they do so with the <code>--safe</code> flag, disabling any plugins not found in the main Jekyll repository. For this reason I now have a <a href="https://github.com/blmoore/blog-staging">staging repo</a> where I&#39;ll (via a simple bash script) build the site locally with whatever custom plug-ins, then copy it to my Github <a href="https://github.com/blmoore/blmoore.github.io">userpage repository</a> and publish.</p>

<p>Other than this issue it&#39;s been reasonably straightforward to make the switch, though I was surprised how much legwork was involved in things like organising <a href="http://realjenius.com/2012/12/01/jekyll-category-tag-paging-feeds/">tag-specific paginated indexes</a> for navigation and custom RSS/Atom feeds. For me, this kind of stuff should come out of the box even in a barebones, for-customisation framework like Jekyll. Thankfully there&#39;s bloggers around who&#39;ve already figured out this stuff, as well as some of the under-documented features (like <a href="http://joshualande.com/short-urls-jekyll/">permalinks</a>).</p>

<p>More recently I&#39;ve been told that the R package <a href="https://blm.io/blog/slidify">slidify</a> is capable of Jekyll-like functionality, and this will soon be spun-off into its own package:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/benjaminlmoore"><a href='https://github.com/benjaminlmoore' class='user-mention'>@benjaminlmoore</a></a> Slidify is also capable of generating static blogs. It will become a separate package <a href="http://t.co/ED09PAhGyW">http://t.co/ED09PAhGyW</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/rmflight"><a href='https://github.com/rmflight' class='user-mention'>@rmflight</a></a></p>&mdash; Ramnath Vaidyanathan (@ramnath_vaidya) <a href="https://twitter.com/ramnath_vaidya/statuses/479422134968524801">June 19, 2014</a></blockquote>

<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>Most of my posts will involve some R analysis so this could end up a better solution for me, as a non-Rubyist. Maybe I&#39;ll be having another big change in a few months time...</p>

		]]></description>
	  </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
